瓦雷利亚末日
伊耿一世（AC1-37 在位）
“征服者”
镶嵌红宝石的瓦雷利亚钢王冠
坦格利安家族征服维斯特洛
雷妮丝
伊耿一世的妹妹和妻子
伊尼斯一世（AC37-42 在位）
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
杰赫里斯一世（AC48-103 在位）
“和解者”“人瑞王”
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
杰赫里斯一世（AC48-103 在位）
“和解者”“人瑞王”
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
亚莉珊（AC36-100）
“善良王后”
杰赫里斯一世的妹妹和妻子
贝尔隆（AC57-101）
“勇敢的”“春晓王子”
杰赫里斯一世的儿子和国王之手
阿莱莎（AC60-84）
贝尔隆的妹妹和妻子
戴蒙
“浪荡王子”
贝尔隆的儿子 韦赛里斯一世的弟弟
戴蒙
“浪荡王子”
贝尔隆的儿子 韦赛里斯一世的弟弟
兰娜尔·瓦列利安
科利斯和雷妮丝的女儿 戴蒙的妻子
贝妮拉·坦格利安
戴蒙与兰娜尔的双胞胎长女
雷妮亚·坦格利安
戴蒙与兰娜尔的双胞胎次女
雷妮拉
韦赛里斯一世的女儿和王储
瓦列利安家族参加王室婚礼
改编自 《血与火：坦格利安王朝史》
[美] 乔治·马丁 著
龙 王 家 族
第一季 第七集
潮头岛 Driftmark
今日我们齐聚海中宝座
Tubī Velario Lentro Ābrāzme
安葬瓦列利安家族的兰娜尔夫人
Laene iēdrarta mōrqittot,
到永恒水域 人鱼王的领地
māzīlarē tubirri Elēdrion ziry umīsilza luo dāriot,
科利斯·瓦列利安
“海蛇”“潮汛之主” 潮头岛伯爵
雷妮丝·坦格利安
“无冕女王” 韦赛里斯的堂姐 科利斯的妻子
从此人鱼王会永远守护她
hannagon Embrurliot gierūlti.
贝妮拉·坦格利安
戴蒙与兰娜尔的双胞胎长女
她将最后一次入海远航
Solion tolijor zijosy pradarose,
雷妮亚·坦格利安
戴蒙与兰娜尔的双胞胎次女
兰娜尔夫人在岸上留下了两位亲生女儿
Ābrāzma Laena rāeniot hen eglio ilvot lanto taloti hembis.
戴蒙·坦格利安
“浪荡王子” 韦赛里斯的弟弟
魏蒙德·瓦列利安
科利斯的弟弟
尽管她们的母亲不再归航
Pōja muña hen zȳho solio āmāzīlus daor,
奥托·海塔尔
王后的父亲 国王之手
她们依然血脉相连
yn ānogrosa gierī ozletaksi humbilza.
海盐淌过瓦列利安的血脉
Velario ānogro rȳ lopor ojāris.
雷妮拉·坦格利安
“王国之光” 龙石岛公主 王储
杰卡里斯·瓦列利安
雷妮拉与兰尼诺的长子
路斯里斯·瓦列利安
雷妮拉与兰尼诺的次子
我们血脉浓稠
Īlvon qumblī iāris.
我们血脉纯正
Īlvon drējī iāris.
韦赛里斯·坦格利安一世
国王
兰尼诺·瓦列利安
科利斯之子 雷妮拉的丈夫
而我们的血脉绝不可淡薄
Se dōrī vajiñagon īlvon bēvilis.
我温婉的侄女
Talus mandus ñuhus.
愿海风如你脊背般坚强
Inkoso kostōbāpis aōhis jelmīs sagon,
愿海域如你灵魂般平静
gīso lykāpas aōhas embis,
伊耿·坦格利安
韦赛里斯与阿莉森的长子
阿莉森·海塔尔
王后 奥托之女
克里斯顿·科尔
御林铁卫
愿渔获如你心灵般充盈
se prūmȳsa lēdāpas aōhas manengīs.
我们来自大海
Hen embār masti.
我们归于大海
Va embrot āmāzīli.
你见到父亲了没？
Have you seen your father?
你的小表妹刚刚失去母亲
Your little cousins have lost their mother.
她们需要安慰
They could use a kind word.
我也需要安慰
I have an equal claim to sympathy.
- 小杰 - 我们应该在赫伦堡
-Jace. -We should be at Harrenhal,
哀悼莱昂诺大人和哈尔温爵士
mourning Lord Lyonel and Ser Harwin.
这不妥当
It would not be appropriate.
瓦列利安是我们的亲人 斯壮不是
The Velaryons are our kin and the Strongs are not.
看着我
Look at me.
你明白吗
Do you understand?
手摇织机
Hand turns loom;
绿线轴 黑线轴
spool of green, spool of black;
龙之血肉
dragons of flesh
编织龙之线
weaving dragons of thread.
海伦娜·坦格利安
韦赛里斯与阿莉森的女儿
手摇织机 绿线轴
Hand turns loom; spool of green...
- 我们一点都不像  - 她是我们的姐妹
-We have nothing in common. -She's our sister.
伊蒙德·坦格利安
韦赛里斯与阿莉森的次子
- 那你娶她 - 如果母亲让我们成婚
-You marry her, then. -I would perform my duty,
- 我自会履行职责 - “如果”
-if mother had only betrothed us. - If only.
这会让家族强大
It would strengthen the family.
保持我们的瓦雷利亚血统纯正
Keep our Valyrian blood pure.
- 她就是个白痴 - 她是你未来的王后
-She's an idiot. -She's your future queen.
我们确实有个
We actually do have
共同之处
one thing in common.
我们都喜欢大长腿
We both fancy creatures with very long legs.
小妞儿！
Wench!
- 再来一杯！- 伊耿
-Another! -Aegon.
……龙之血肉 编织龙之线
...dragon's flesh, weaving dragons of thread.
拉里斯·斯壮
“弯足” 赫伦堡伯爵
莱昂诺·斯壮的儿子从我们到这就一直盯着您 陛下
Lyonel Strong's son's been staring at you since the moment we arrived, Your Grace.
毫无避忌
Unabashedly.
他只是在显摆 克里斯顿爵士
It is only a look of pride, Ser Criston.
拉里斯是新任赫伦堡伯爵
Larys is the new Lord of Harrenhal.
我的位子和高潮城
Both my seat and High Tide
有一天都是你的 路斯里斯
will be yours one day, Lucerys.
当然 你哥哥会当上国王
Your brother will be king, of course.
他会出席数不清的御前会议和庆典
He'll sit on endless councils and ceremonies,
但做了潮汛之主 就能统治大海
but Lord of the Tides rules the sea.
对不起
Sorry.
我不想要
I don't want it.
这是你生来就有的权利 小子
It's your birthright, lad.
如果我当了潮头岛伯爵 就意味着所有人都死了
If I'm the Lord of Driftmark, it means everyone's dead.
- 请您节哀 -谢谢 谢谢
-I'm very sorry. -Thank you. Thank you.
外婆……
Grandma...
我不想母亲去世
I don't want Mother to be gone.
卡尔·奎瑞
兰尼诺·瓦列利安的男伴
把你主子找回来
Retrieve your patron.
哥哥
Brother.
你的女儿们和母亲长得一模一样
Your girls are the very image of their mother.
既是安慰 也是痛苦
A comfort and an anguish,
我很清楚这滋味
as I well remember.
诸神有时很残忍
The gods can be cruel.
看起来对你尤为残忍
It seems they've been especially cruel to you.
是啊
Yes.
你应该和我们一起回君临
You should return with us to King's Landing.
是时候回家了
It's time that you came home.
潘托斯才是我的家……
Pentos is my home...
- 也是孩子们的家 - 戴蒙……
-and that of my children. -Daemon...
我知道我们有过种种分歧
I know we've had our differences,
但都过了这么久了 就随它们去吧
but let them pass with the years.
如果你想要
There's a place for you in my court
我就在朝中给你留个位子
if that's something you should need.
我要⻗……我什么都不要
I need... nothing.
弟弟
Brother.
请节哀 王子殿下
I'm sorry for your loss, my Prince.
不管是多肥的水蛭 永远没有吸饱的时候
No matter how fat the leech grows, it always wants for another meal.
去睡觉
Go to bed.
- 但是 母亲 - 去睡觉
-But, Mother-- -Go to bed.
我要去睡了 爱玛
I'm going to bed, Aemma.
需要我照看阿莉森王后吗 陛下？
Shall I see after Queen Alicent, Your Grace?
哈罗德·维斯特林
御林铁卫队长
不 哈罗德爵士
No, Ser Harrold.
你去守夜班 克里斯顿爵士
You have the night's watch, Ser Criston.
遵命 队长大人
Lord Commander.
弟弟？
Brother?
滚回床上睡
Get to bed.
她想回家
She wanted to come home
但他拒绝了
and he denied her.
戴蒙只是做了他觉得最好的选择
Daemon did what he thought best.
戴蒙只会做最利于自己的选择
Daemon only ever does what is best for Daemon.
兰娜尔需要我们的学士
Laena needed our maesters.
潘托斯的医生和我们的学士
The surgeons in Pentos are as well-trained
一样医术高明
as our maesters.
你这是因诸神之举迁怒他人
You are looking to place blame for an act of the gods.
也许这正是诸神对我们的嘲弄……
Mayhaps the gods have scorned us...
因为我们贪得无厌 傲慢自大
for our insatiable pride.
王冠本是你的
The crown was yours
却硬生生被大议会上那些蠢货夺走
until those fools at the Great Council plucked it from your head.
难道你的丈夫想替你夺回王冠 就如此不堪？
Is it such a terrible thing for your husband to wish to win it back?
今天晚上 就让我们抛开虚伪 坦诚相对
Tonight of all nights, let us lay aside this falsehood.
真正驱使你这么做的 不是为妻子伸张正义
It is not justice for your wife that drives you.
而是实现自己的野心
It is your own ambition.
是你对王座的野心
'Tis desire for the throne,
如果不是为了自己 就是为了你的子孙后代
if not for yourself, then for the scions of your house.
我早就放弃对王位的念想了
I gave up the idea of wearing a crown a generation ago.
是你 我的夫君 不愿放弃执念
It is you, lord husband, who refuses to abandon this pursuit,
即使它害了我们的孩子
even now, at the cost of our children.
如果不是为了家族传承
What is this brief mortal life...
我们这短暂平凡的一生又有什么意义？
if not the pursuit of legacy?
传承后人 也许就是你一生所求 科利斯
Legacy may be why you live your life, Corlys.
我想让兰娜尔的女儿贝妮拉继承潮头岛
I want Driftmark to pass through Laena's line to Baela.
她是真正的瓦列利安血脉
To true Velaryon blood.
趁大家都在 现在就宣布此事
Declare it now, while all are gathered here,
我们可以说 这是为了纪念兰娜尔
and we will say that is how we will honor Laena's memory.
就这么剥夺我们儿子的继承权？
And disinherit our son?
他会成为王夫
He will be the King Consort.
他的儿子有一天会登上铁王座
His son will one day sit the Iron Throne.
你是要我对那两个被阴影笼罩的孩子
You would have me cast an even darker shadow
落井下石
over those little boys than already exists.
现在没有旁人 夫君
We are alone here, husband.
你可以说出真相 我们都心知肚明
You can speak the plain truth as we both know it:
雷妮拉的孩子不是你的血脉
Rhaenyra's children are not of your blood.
但兰娜尔的孩子是
But Laena's are.
她们就是兰娜尔留给我们的传承
They are her legacy.
历史不会记得血脉
History does not remember blood.
只会铭记姓氏
It remembers names.
兰尼诺这几年都不大安分
Laenor has been restless for years,
到了现在 他更是指望不上
but now, he will be useless.
甚至更糟
Or worse.
我们的婚姻不过一场闹剧 我比谁都清楚
I know better than anyone that our marriage is a farce.
但至少我还在努力维持体面
But I at least make the effort to maintain appearances.
因为你有更重的包袱
You have more to lose.
是啊 既然父亲立我为王储 这便是我的命运
Yes, well, that has been my lot since my father named me heir.
我们确实曾经试着……
We did try...
去怀个孩子
to conceive a child.
我们尽了最大努力去履行自己的责任
We performed our duty as best we could.
但一切都是徒劳
But to no avail.
整个过程毫无乐趣
There was no joy in it.
但我在其他地方找到了乐趣
I found that elsewhere.
被人渴望的感觉真不错
It felt good to be desired.
我知道哈尔温爵士对你非常……
I understand Ser Harwin was quite...
忠诚
devoted to you.
没错 他的确如此
Yes, he was.
我也很信任他
And I trusted him.
我应该阻止哈尔温爵士回到河间地
Should've forbidden Ser Harwin from returning to the Riverlands.
伊耿征服之后赫伦堡就流传着可怕的诅咒 现在看来还是那么强大
Harren's curse is said to be as strong now as it was after the Conquest.
那不过是个鬼故事
That's a ghost story,
奥托爵士和王后乐于拿它大做文章
one Ser Otto and the Queen would gladly exploit.
我不相信阿莉森会这么冷血地杀人
I do not believe Alicent capable of cold murder.
我们每个人都可能堕落
Each of us is capable of depravity.
程度远超你的想象
And more than you would believe.
如果说的是你 那我确实相信
I believe it of you.
如果你想指责我堕落了
If you're accusing me of some depravity,
不妨把话说明白点
you'll need to be more specific.
我一直孤身一人
I've been alone.
- 你抛弃了我  - 我放过了你
-You abandoned me. -I spared you.
- 那时你还是个孩子 - 没错
-You were a child. -Yes.
没错 那时我还是个孩子
Yes, I was a child.
看看没有你 我的人生变成了什么样子
And look at what my life became without you.
可笑的悲剧
Droll tragedy.
反过来说 你以为我的人生又过成了什么样？
And I wonder what you think of mine by comparison?
我对你这几年一无所知
I know little of it.
你爱过她吗？
Did you love her?
我们很幸福
We were happy enough.
嗯 那就算很了不起了
Well, that in itself is a great achievement.
- 我很抱歉 - 不必
-I am sorry. -Don't be.
至少我还能哀悼逝去的爱人
I am at least allowed to mourn my losses.
雷妮拉
Rhaenyra.
我不再是个孩子了
I'm no longer a child.
我想要你
I want you.
操
Fuck.
瓦格哈尔
曾属于兰娜尔·瓦列利安的龙
乖！
Dohaerās!
乖 瓦格哈尔！冷静！
Dohaerās, Vhagar! Lykirī!
冷静！
Lykirī!
冷静
Lykirī.
飞！
Sōvēs!
乖 瓦格哈尔！飞！
Dohaerās, Vhagar! Sōvēs!
哇！
Yeah!
小杰 小杰
Jace, Jace.
小杰 醒醒 醒醒
Jace, wake up. Wake up.
- 有人偷走了瓦格哈尔 - 什么？
-Someone stole Vhagar. - What?
那是谁？
Who is it?
小杰 我们怎么办？
Jace, what are we doing?
- 就是他 - 是我没错
-It's him. -It's me.
- 瓦格哈尔是我妈妈的龙 - 你妈妈已经死了
-Vhagar is my mother's dragon. -Your mother's dead.
- 瓦格哈尔现在有新骑手了 - 她是属于我的
-And Vhagar has a new rider now. -She was mine to claim.
那你就该早点去驯服她
Then you should've claimed her!
也许你的表兄弟们会帮你找一头猪骑
Maybe your cousins can find you a pig to ride.
那很适合你
It would suit you.
你再敢过来 我就拿你喂我的龙！
Come at me again and I'll feed you to my dragon!
你会像你父亲一样在火焰中尖叫着死去！
You will die screaming in flames just as your father did!
野种
Bastards.
我父亲还活着
My father's still alive.
他还不知道 是吗 斯壮大人？
He doesn't know, does he, Lord Strong?
小杰！
Jace!
马上住手！
Cease this at once!
让开！
Get away!
王子殿下 王子殿下 让我看看
My Prince, my Prince. Let me see.
诸神保佑
Gods be good.
你怎么能让这样的事情发生？
How could you allow such a thing to happen?
给我查个清楚
I will have answers.
王子们应该是在睡觉的 国王陛下
The princes were supposed to be abed, My King.
是谁在值夜？
Who had the watch?
陛下 小王子受到了表亲们的攻击
Young prince was attacked by his own cousins, Your Grace.
你们曾发誓要保护捍卫我的血脉！
You swore oaths to protect and defend my blood!
我很抱歉 陛下
I'm very sorry, Your Grace.
塔雅
王后的侍女
御林铁卫从来没试过 要阻止王子伤害王子
The Kingsguard has never had to defend princes from princes,
- 陛下 - 这不是我要的答复！
-Your Grace. -That is no answer!
会痊愈的 对吗 学士？
It will heal, will it not, maester?
血肉会愈合
The flesh will heal.
但是眼睛保不住了 王后陛下
But the eye is lost, Your Grace.
- 当时你在哪里？ - 我吗？
-Where were you? -Me?
- 打我干什么？ - 弟弟被人欺负的时候
-What was that for? -That was nothing compared to
你却喝个烂醉如泥
the abuse your brother suffered
这一巴掌算得了什么 你这个傻瓜
while you were drowning in your cups, you fool.
这是怎么回事？
What is the meaning of this?
贝妮拉 雷妮亚 发生了什么？
Baela, Rhaena! What happened?
发生了什么？
What happened?
小杰？
Jace?
小路！
Luke!
让我看看 让我看看
Show me. Show me.
- 谁干的？ - 他们打我！
-Who did this? -They attacked me!
- 他打了贝妮拉！ - 他打断了小路的鼻子！
-He attacked Baela! -He broke Luke's nose!
他偷了我妈妈的龙！
He stole my mother's dragon!
- 够了 - 他还想杀了小杰！
-Enough. -He was gonna kill Jace!
- 我什么也没做！ - 够了——
-I didn't do anything! -Enough--
应该听我儿子怎么说！
It should be my son telling the tale!
- 他叫我们—— - 安静！
-He called us-- - Silence!
他叫我们野种
He called us bastards.
伊蒙德……
Aemond...
我要知道事情的真相
I will have the truth of what happened.
- 现在就说 - 还有什么可问的？
-Now. -What else is there to hear?
你儿子残了 她儿子干的
Your son has been maimed. Her son is responsible.
- 这是一场令人遗憾的意外 - 意外?
-It was a regrettable accident. -Accident?
路斯里斯王子带了一把匕首来伏击
The Prince Lucerys brought a blade to the ambush.
他想要杀了我儿子
He meant to kill my son.
是我的儿子们受到攻击
It was my sons who were attacked
他们不得不自卫
and forced to defend themselves.
他们遭受了恶毒的侮辱
Vile insults were levied against them.
什么侮辱？
What insults?
有人胆敢公开质疑我儿子们的正统血脉
The legitimacy of my sons' birth was put loudly to question.
- 什么？ - 他叫我们野种
-What? -He called us bastards.
陛下 我的儿子们是铁王座的顺位继承人
My sons are in line to inherit the Iron Throne, Your Grace.
这是最为严重的叛国罪行
This is the highest of treasons.
伊蒙德王子必须受到严厉讯问
Prince Aemond must be sharply questioned
让他交代到底是从哪里听到的这些谣言
so we might learn where he heard such slanders.
就因为一句侮辱的话？
Over an insult?
我的儿子失去了一只眼睛
My son has lost an eye.
告诉我 孩子 你从哪里听来这谣言的？
You tell me, boy. Where did you hear this lie?
所谓侮辱不过是训练场上打闹喊话
The insult was training yard bluster.
- 男孩子在一起都这样 没什么 - 伊蒙德……
-The lot of boys. It was nothing. -Aemond...
我在问你问题
I asked you a question.
我想知道 孩子们的父亲兰尼诺爵士去哪儿了
Where is Ser Laenor, I wonder? The boys' father?
对于这件事 也许他有话要说
Perhaps he might have something to say in the matter.
是啊 兰尼诺爵士呢
Yes. Where is Ser Laenor?
我不知道 陛下 我…… 睡不着
I do not know, Your Grace. I... could not find sleep.
就出门散心了
I had gone out to walk.
想必是跟他的小侍从们找乐子去了
Entertaining his young squires, I would venture.
伊蒙德
Aemond...
看着我
look at me.
你的国王命令你必须回答
Your king demands an answer.
谁告诉你的这个谣言？
Who spoke these lies to you?
伊耿说的
It was Aegon.
我？
Me?
那你呢 小子？
And you, boy?
你又是从哪听到的这些诽谤？
Where did you hear such calumnies?
伊耿！你给我说实话
Aegon! Tell me the truth of it!
我们都知道 父亲
We know, Father.
大家都知道
Everyone knows.
瞧他们那样
Just look at them.
我们必须停止这样无休无止地内斗！
This interminable infighting must cease!
所有人都给我住手！
All of you!
我们是一家人！
We are family!
现在你们各自道歉 向对方表达善意
Now make your apologies and show good will to one another.
你们的父亲 祖父和国王命令你们
Your father, your grandsire, your king demands it!
这就够了吗
That is insufficient.
伊蒙德受到了永久伤害 我的国王陛下
Aemond has been damaged, permanently, My King.
“善意”无法让他完好如初
"Good will" cannot make him whole.
我很清楚 阿莉森 我也没法让他的眼睛复原
I know, Alicent, but I cannot restore his eye.
是啊 因为被人夺走了
No, because it's been taken.
- 那你想让我怎么办？ - 血债必须血偿
-What would you have me do? -There is a debt to be paid.
让她儿子赔我们一只眼睛
I shall have one of her son's eyes in return.
- 我亲爱的妻子 - 他是你的儿子 韦赛里斯
-My dear wife. -He is your son, Viserys.
你的血脉
Your blood.
请不要
Do not...
让愤怒左右你的判断
allow your temper to guide your judgment.
要是国王不主持公道 王后自会主持
If the King will not seek justice, the Queen will.
克里斯顿爵士……
Ser Criston...
给我挖了路斯里斯·瓦列利安的眼睛
bring me the eye of Lucerys Velaryon.
- 母亲！ - 阿莉森
-Mother! -Alicent.
他可以选择留下哪只 我儿子可没享受到这等福利
He can choose which eye to keep, a privilege he did not grant my son.
你不能这么做
You will do no such thing.
- 都不许动 - 不行 你向我宣誓过
-Stay your hand. -No, you are sworn to me!
我发誓会护您周全 王后陛下
As your protector, my Queen.
阿莉森 这件事…… 到此为止
Alicent, this matter... is finished.
听懂了吗？
Do you understand?
所有人都给我记住
And let it be known:
倘若有任何人胆敢对雷妮拉公主之子的血统
anyone whose tongue dares to question the birth
提出质疑 散布谣言
of Princess Rhaenyra's sons
我会割了你们的舌头
should have it removed.
谢谢您 父亲
Thank you, Father.
- 陛下 - 阿莉森！回到你的国王身边来！
-Your Grace. -Alicent! Stay with the King!
不要再往前走了！
Hold your approach!
- 别过去 克里斯顿爵士！ - 阿莉森！
-Do not, Ser Criston! -Alicent!
别过去 克里斯顿爵士！
Do not, Ser Criston!
阿莉森！
Alicent!
不！
No!
你不许动 科尔！
Stay your hand, Cole!
你做得太过火了
You've gone too far.
我？
I?
除了满足他人对我的要求和期待 我又做了什么过火的事？
What have I done but what was expected of me?
一直以来我都在维护着我们的王国 家庭和律法
Forever upholding the kingdom, the family, the law.
- 你却藐视一切 随心所欲 - 阿莉森 放开她！
-While you flout all to do as you please. -Alicent, let her go!
你的责任呢？你的牺牲呢？
Where is duty? Where is sacrifice?
一次次被你那双美丽的脚肆意践踏
It's trampled under your pretty foot again.
把刀子放下 阿莉森
Release the blade, Alicent.
现在你害我儿子少了一只眼睛
And now you take my son's eye,
即便这样 你还是这么理直气壮
and to even that, you feel entitled.
你不累吗？
Exhausting, wasn't it?
总是躲藏在公正得体的长袍之下
Hiding beneath the cloak of your own righteousness.
现在大家都见识到你这副面孔了
But now they see you as you are.
不用为我伤心 母亲
Do not mourn me, Mother.
这是一桩公平的交易
It was a fair exchange.
我虽然少了只眼睛
I may have lost an eye...
但得到了一条龙
but I gained a dragon.
相关事件就到此为止
This proceeding is at an end.
首相大人求见 陛下
The Hand, Your Grace.
有话说话
Say your piece.
事到如今还能说什么呢？
Now, what piece is that?
我刚刚的所作所为……
I've conducted myself in a manner...
即便不以王后的标准看待
unbefitting my station.
依然有失体面
Or any other.
我失去了理智……
I lost composure...
袭击了公主
assaulted the Princess.
大家已经在传闲话 怀疑我是不是疯了
Already the word is spreading, the gossip speculating that I've gone mad.
你说得都对
All true.
我让自己丢脸了
I disgraced myself.
我让丈夫永远都会偏向她女儿那边
And ensured my husband's favor will forever rest on her.
但是呢……
And yet...
我从没见过这样的你 我的女儿
I've never seen that side of you, my daughter.
我一度怀疑你没有这样的一面
I even doubted its existence.
- 丑恶的一面 我很后悔 - 我们本来就在玩一场丑恶的游戏
-It was an ugly thing. I regret it. -We play an ugly game.
如今 我这辈子第一次
And now, for the first time,
看到了你想赢的决心
I see that you have the determination to win it.
- 雷妮拉—— - 你也看清她的为人了
-Rhaenyra-- -You see her for what she is.
瞧瞧国王的偏执把她惯成什么样子
What the King's stubbornness has wrought.
- 他会跟我说些什么？ - 他会原谅你的
-What will he say to me? -He'll forgive you.
不然他还能做什么
What else can he do?
快去找他吧 显出悔恨的样子
Now go to him, be penitent,
为你儿子的伤辩解一番
plead the injury to your son.
控制好情绪不要激动
Keep a grip on your passions.
我向你保证 你我联手一定能赢得这场游戏
And I promise you, in time, you and I together will prevail.
伊蒙德撒的野
What that rogue Aemond has done
为我们赢得了瓦格哈尔
in winning Vhagar to our side.
孩子说得对
The boy was right.
这比他付出的代价值一千倍
It's worth a thousand times the price he paid.
肯定要留疤 但伤口会愈合的
You will scar, but the wound will heal.
瓦雷利亚钢的创口都很平整
Valyrian steel cuts clean.
诸神啊
Gods.
大家都还好么？
Is everyone all right?
最糟糕的伤是断了鼻子
A broken nose is the worst.
谢谢你 学士
Thank you, maester.
先退下吧
Leave us.
你俩也出去
You as well.
今天惹的祸已经够多了
You've already found enough trouble today.
好的 母亲
Yes, Mother.
我应该在场的
I should've been there.
不如把这句话当咱们的族语吧
Those should be our house words.
我曾和那么多可怕的敌人战斗
I have fought dreadful enemies,
却没能保护好自己的妹妹
but I could not defend my dear sister
她远离家乡 吃了那么多苦
far from home and in agony.
- 我也没能保护好你 - 坐吧
-I could not defend you. -Sit down.
伊蒙德叫我们的儿子野种
Aemond called our sons bastards.
我让你失望了 雷妮拉
I have failed you, Rhaenyra.
我们的婚姻
Our marriage...
我尽力了
I tried.
我们的儿子
Our boys...
- 我真的爱他们  - 我知道
-I do love them. -I know.
真的很爱
Deeply.
但是 也许
But I have not, mayhaps...
还是爱得不够吧
loved them enough.
我们同床共枕那几次
I had hoped to bear your children.
我希望能怀上你的孩子
The few times we lay together.
如果成功 可能一切就都不同了
Things might've been different.
我痛恨诸神让我成为这个样子
I hate the gods for making me as they did.
我不觉得
I do not.
你高贵正直
You are an honorable man
心地善良
with a good heart.
这很难得
It's a rare thing.
多年以前我们就达成了协议
We made an arrangement all those years ago
履行职责的同时
to do our duty and...
不耽误彼此寻找快乐
yet explore happiness.
但有些时候
But there are times
我觉得职责与快乐无法兼顾
I think when these things cannot mutually exist.
卡尔爵士很快就会重返石阶列岛的战场
Ser Qarl will return soon to the fighting in the Stepstones.
但我会捡起承诺 留在你身边
But I recommit myself to you.
巩固我们的家族 为你来日登基做好准备
And to strengthening our house as we prepare you for your ascension.
把我们的儿子养育成为合格的王子
I will raise our sons to be princes of the realm.
- 兰尼诺   - 你值得比我更好的
-Laenor-- -You deserve better than what I have been.
你需要丈夫在身边
You deserve a husband.
我已经让人在船上备好了酒
I've asked them to have wine ready for you on the ship.
喝了睡个好觉
To help you sleep.
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
韦赛里斯
Viserys...
这事不必再提了
We will speak no more of it.
火 是如此神奇的力量
Fire is such strange power.
坦格利安家族拥有的一切都归功于火
Everything that House Targaryen possesses is owed to it.
但火也让我们两人痛失所爱
Yet it has cost us both what we loved.
恐怕瓦列利安家族早就明白
Perhaps the Velaryons knew the truth of it.
大海才是更好的盟友
The sea is the better ally.
烈火是牢笼
Fire is a prison.
大海赐予了解脱
The sea offers an escape.
这是正义的扭曲
A perversion of justice.
小王子 含冤受辱
The young prince...defiled.
此等暴行 骇人听闻
An outrage.
没错
Indeed.
如果您需要以眼还眼 我愿随时效劳
If it's an eye you want to balance the scales, I am your servant.
倒也不必如此
That will not be necessary.
但你的忠诚我铭记于心
But your devotion has not gone unnoticed.
危险的时代已经到来
These are dangerous times.
迟早有一天 我需要一个你这样的朋友
The day will doubtless come when I require such a friend.
既有高超技艺 又能独当一面
With not only skill but discretion as well.
随时等候您的差遣 王后陛下
I shall await your call, my Queen.
我需要你 叔叔
I need you, Uncle.
我一个人应付不来绿党
Kastoti mērpī naejuragon koston daor.
让我们把血脉结合
Īlvor ānogri īlot letagon,
就像征服者伊耿和他的姐妹一样
hae Aegot Ērinȳ zȳhom mandȳma hāedromā.
只有你来做我的丈夫 我的王夫
Ñuhys valzȳrys belmōr aōma issarome,
才不会有人轻易挑战我的继承权
ñuho drīvo bē epvor lykemiluks daor.
瓦列利安属于大海
Velaria embōñar issi.
而你和我
Yn ao nykē
属于火焰
perzōñi iksi.
我们命中注定要一起燃烧
Hen prānot hae mērȳ zālagon indīliks.
兰尼诺不死 我们没法结婚
We could not marry unless Laenor were dead.
我知道
I know.
我听说你在石阶列岛立了赫赫战功
I've heard about your exploits in the Stepstones,
卡尔爵士
Ser Qarl.
人们称道你是个身手不凡的骑士
Said to be a knight of remarkable skill.
过奖了 大人
You flatter me, m'lord.
但可惜啊 平民出身
But alas, common-born.
一个无产骑士 却有着领主的品味
You're a landless knight with a lord's taste.
兰尼诺爵士对我非常慷慨
Ser Laenor's been kind to me.
你知道吗
Do you know...
狭海对面有些地方
there are places across the Narrow Sea...
没人会在意一个人的名字
where it doesn't matter what a man's name is?
只在乎他兜里有多少金子
Only how much gold he possesses.
大人 您想让我做什么
What are you asking of me, m'lord?
一场干脆利落的死亡
A quick death.
记得留个见证人
One with witnesses.
我不会做一个
I will not be a tyrant.
依靠恐怖统治的暴君
And rule through terror.
只会散播恐怖才叫暴君
A tyrant rules only through terror.
但无人惧怕的君王 也不会拥有权力
If the King isn't feared, he is powerless.
如果你想做一个强大的女王 固然需要臣民爱戴你崇敬你
If you are to be a strong queen, you must cultivate love and respect, yes,
但也必须让他们畏惧你
but your subjects must fear you.
谁让你进来的？
Who let you in here?
你到我父亲的大厅来做什么？
Why are you in my father's hall?
你一直都看不起我
You have always looked down on me.
我确实爱兰尼诺
I do love Laenor.
那就赐他慈悲
Then grant him this kindness.
让他解脱
Set him free.
你以为自己是什么身份
You forget yourself.
大人 求您不要！
My lord. Please!
我去叫守卫！
I'll alert the guards!
这样会让科利斯大人和雷妮丝公主
This will cost Lord Corlys and Princess Rhaenys
失去他们现在唯一的孩子
their only remaining child.
王国上下会议论纷纷 认为我是那个幕后黑手
And the realm will whisper that I was somehow responsible.
不！
No!
让他们议论
Let them whisper.
不！
No!
你们是怎么当的守卫？
How did you let this happen?
我自家厅堂也他妈能出这种事？
In my fucking hall?
告诉我！
Tell me!
我们知道真相 敌人蒙在鼓里
We will know the truth of it and our enemies won't.
他们会害怕 畏惧我们的能耐
They will fear what else we might be capable of.
在雷妮拉额头写下的高等瓦雷利亚文字意为“火”
在戴蒙额头写下的高等瓦雷利亚文字意为“血”
两支血脉 合而为一
Hen lantoti ānogar, Va sȳndroti vāedroma.
幽幽火焰 阴影颂歌
Mēro perzot gīhoti, Elēdroma iārza sīr.
两心同出 火峰余烬
Izulī ampā perzī, Prūmī lanti sēteksi.
明日诺于杯中 天上群星为证
Hen jenȳ māzīlarion, Qēlossa ozūndesi.
誓言穿越时间 白日黑夜不休
Sȳndroro ōñō jēdo, Rȳ kīvia mazvestraksi.